Oliver Butterworth Papers 2000.0052
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Oliver Butterworth Papers
undated, 1934-1996.
2000.0052
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
5.25 Linear feet
The papers of Oliver Butterworth, native of Connecticut and educator and author of children's books. The collection contains correspondence, notes, drafts, manuscripts, galleys, proofs, artwork, scripts and published books pertaining to Butterworth's career and interests.
Butterworth, Oliver.
Biography
Oliver Butterworth, educator and author of children's books, was born 23 May 1915, in Hartford, Connecticut, the son of Paul McMillan and Clarabel (Smith) Butterworth. He attended Dartmouth College (A.B., 1937) and did his graduate study at Harvard University (1941) and Middlebury College (M.A., 1947). Butterworth taught at Kent School ( Kent, Connecticut, 1937-1947) and Junior School ( West Hartford, Connecticut, 1947-1949). Beginning in 1947, he taught English at Hartford College for Women ( Hartford, Connecticut) until the late 1980s. He was awarded the New York Herald Tribune Spring Festival of Books prize (1960) for The Trouble with Jenny's Ear and the Lewis Carroll Shelf award (1970) for The Enormous Egg. A trustee of the Hartford College for Women and the Mark Twain Memorial (1958-1962), Butterworth died of cancer 17 September 1990, in West Hartford, Connecticut.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, notes, drafts, manuscripts, galleys, proofs, artwork, scripts and published books pertaining to Butterworth's career and interests. His most well-known story, The Enormous Egg, was also performed on stage, television and film and the collection contains the scripts, teleplay and screenplay for these adaptations, as well as correspondence, reviews and contracts. The collection also includes the manuscripts for several unpublished stories, sonnets and poems. A collection of Butterworth's correspondence was published in the 1980s covering the years 1934 through 1939. The folder in the Correspondence series with these dates includes photocopies of these letters, although some appear to be incomplete and without a discernable order.
Organization
Series I: Personal papers, ( undated, 1934-1993 ) includes correspondence both to and from Oliver and Miriam Butterworth.
Series II: Unpublished Works, ( undated, 1953-1954 ) contains shorts stories, poems and manuscripts.
Series III: Published Works, ( undated, 1954-1996 ) includes manuscripts, proofs, correspondence and artwork pertaining to Butterworth's published stories.
Series IV: Photographs, ( undated, 1957 ) contains five images associated with The Enormous Egg.
Series V: 2008 Addition, ( 1952-2005 ) contains books, news clippings, correspondence, fliers, photographs, publications, galley proof, and awards.
Arrangement
The correspondence has been arranged chronologically and the unpublished materials alphabetically by title. Published Works have been arranged in a way to parallel the creative process, from drafts and sketches through the contract, correspondence and proofs.
Separated Material
Bud
The Enormous Egg
English
German
Japanese Dodd CLC A 3028
Swedish
The First Blueberry Pig
The Narrow Passage
The Trouble with Jenny's Ear
A Visit to the Big House (hardcover)
English and Spanish (paperback)
The Read Aloud Handbook by Jim Trelease
Butterworth 2000-0052.vr1
General note
The following titles have been removed from the collection and catalogued.
Bibliography
Fourth Book of Junior Authors and Illustrators, edited by Doris de Montreville and Elizabeth D.Crawford, Wilson, 1978.
Twentieth-Century Children's Writers, fourth edition, St. James Press, 1995.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Archives and Special Collections by Mrs. Miriam Butterworth in January 2001.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Children's literature--American 20th century.; Children's literature--Connecticut authors.; Children's literature--Manuscripts.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Northeast Children's Literature Collection.; Notes.; Proofs.; Publications.; Scripts.; Works of Art.
- Series I: Personal papers, undated, 1934-1993
  - Class Notes and Lectures (not Hartford College for Women), undated, 1969-1979 (Box 1:1)
  - Correspondence from Oliver Butterworth, undated, 1934-1961 (Box 1:2)
  - Correspondence from publishers, 1973-1993 (Box 1:3)
  - Correspondence to Oliver Butterworth, undated, 1949-1994 (Box 1:4)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 1:5)
  - Hartford College for Women, 1958-1991 (Box 1:6)
  - Letters to the Editor (photocopies), undated, 1970-1973 (Box 1:7)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated, 1959-1988 (Box 1:8)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1966-1984 (Box 8:92)
  - Obituaries and tributes, 1990 (Box 1:9)
  - Personal, undated (Box 1:10)
- Series II: Unpublished Works, undated, 1953-1954
  - Art--general, undated (Box 1:11)
  - Art--general, undated (Box 8:93)
  - "Decisions, Decisions", undated (Box 1:12)
  - "Forbidden Tree"
    - Pages 1 - 73, undated (Box 1:13)
    - Pages 74 - 189, undated (Box 1:14)
    - Pages 190 - 300, undated (Box 1:15)
    - Pages 301 - 422, undated (Box 1:16)
    - Second Draft, Pages 1 - 85, undated (Box 2:17)
    - Second Draft, Pages 86 - 137, undated (Box 2:18)
    - Second Draft, Pages 138 - 248, undated (Box 2:19)
    - Second Draft, Pages 249 - 340, undated (Box 2:20)
    - Second Draft, Pages 341 - 434, undated (Box 2:21)
    - Second Draft, Pages 435 - 476, undated (Box 2:22)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 2:23)
    - Synopsis by Chapter, undated (Box 2:24)
  - "Fruit Experiment", undated (Box 2:25)
  - "How Uncle Beazley became a Triceratops"--essay, undated (Box 2:26)
  - "Inner Voice", undated (Box 2:27)
  - Poems and Sonnets, undated (Box 2:28)
  - "Princess Mira", undated (Box 2:29)
  - "The Special World of Children's Books", undated (Box 2:30)
  - "Tableau Vivant", undated (Box 2:31)
  - "Telephone", undated (Box 2:32)
  - "The Tempest in a Teapot", undated (Box 2:33)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 2:34)
  - "The Wind and the Rain"
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 2:35)
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 2:36)
  - "The Writer's Guide", undated (Box 2:37)
- Series III: Published Works, undated, 1954-1996
  - The Enormous Egg, ( Little, Brown 1956), undated, 1954-1995
    General note
    See also "How Uncle Beazley..."
    - Research, undated (Box 8:95)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1954-1995 (Box 3:38)
    - Chapters 1, 2, 17 (unannotated), undated (Box 3:39)
    - Manuscript, undated
      - Pages 1 - 24 (Box 3:40)
      - Pages 25 - 57 (Box 3:41)
      - Pages 58 - 83 (Box 3:42)
      - Pages 84 - 107 (Box 3:43)
    - Manuscript with reader's marks, undated (Box 3:44)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 8:97)
    - Book Contract, 1955 (Box 8:94)
    - Proof, undated (Box 8:96)
    - Ephemera, undated (Box 8:100)
    - Abridged version, undated (Box 3:45)
    - Newspaper clippings (Book), undated, 1956-1979 (Box 3:46)
    - NBC teleplay
      - Manuscript, undated (Box 3:47)
      - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 3:48)
      - Newspaper clippings and publications, undated, 1967-1968 (Box 3:49)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1967-1994 (Box 8:98)
    - Stage Productions
      - Hartford Stage script, undated (Box 3:50)
      - Hartford Stage correspondence, undated (Box 4:51)
      - Hartford Stage newspaper clippings, 1981 (Box 899)
      - Opera Delaware correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 4:52)
      - Opera Delaware pre-production information, 1992-1993 (Box 4:53)
      - Windsor Jesters Children's Travel Troupe playscript, undated (Box 4:54)
    - Film Adaptation and Production
      - Correspondence, 1963-1996 (Box 4:55)
      - Draft script, undated (Box 4:56)
      - Script (Boxer), undated (Box 4:57)
    - University of California at Berkeley study, 1969-1970 (Box 4:58)
  - The Trouble with Jenny's Ear ( Little, Brown 1960), undated, 1958-1993
    - Synopsis, undated (Box 4:59)
    - Research and notes, undated, 1955 (Box 4:60)
    - Manuscript, "Working copy A", undated (Box 4:61)
    - Manuscript, "Working copy B", undated (Box 4:62)
    - Manuscript deletions from copy 1 and 2, undated (Box 5:63)
    - Setting copy, undated (Box 6:64)
    - Art, undated (Box 5:65)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1993 (Box 5:66)
    - Book Contract, 1958 (Box 8:101)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 8:102)
    - Play script, MacDuffie School for Girls, 1966 (Box 5:67)
    - Reviews, undated, 1960-1965 (Box 5:68)
  - The Narrow Passage ( Little, Brown 1973), undated, 1956-1987
    - Research, undated (Box 5:69)
    - Manuscript, Working copy, undated (Box 5:70)
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 5:71)
    - Manuscript with typesetting notes, undated (Box 5:72)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 6:73)
    - Art, undated (Box 8:105)
    - Galleys, undated (Box 8:104)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1973 (Box 6:74)
    - Book Contract, 1971 (Box 8:103)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated, 1973-1987 (Box 6:75)
  - The First Blueberry Pig ( Stone Man Press 1986), undated, 1986
    - Dummy, notes, correspondence, undated, 1986 (Box 6:76)
  - A Visit to the Big House ( Families in Crisis 1987), undated, 1985-1993
    - Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box 6:77)
    - Contracts and legal documents, 1988 (Box 6:78)
    - Research surveys--Adults, undated (Box 6:79)
    - Research surveys--Children, undated (Box 6:80)
    - Research, undated (Box 6:81)
    - First draft, undated (Box 6:82)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 6:83)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 8:106)
    - Art, undated (Box 6:84)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1986 (Box 8:107)
    - Reviews, 1989-1993 (Box 6:85)
    - Ephemera, undated (Box 6:86)
  - Orrie's Run, undated, 1973-1985
    - Research, undated, 1974-1986 (Box 7:87)
    - Outline and draft notes, undated (Box 7:88)
    - Manuscript, incomplete copy, undated (Box 7:89)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1985 (Box 7:90)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 7:91)
- Series IV: Photographs, undated, 1957
  - Photographs (children), 1957 (Box 7:108)
  - Photographs (author and book), undated (Box 7:109)
- Series V: 2008 Addition
  - 3 Books, Fliers, Clippings, Correspondence, Photographs, Publications, Galley Proof, Awards, 1952-2005; 0.5 Linear feet Documents organized in folders and envelopes. (Box 2008-0061_9)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects Include: The Enormous Egg Production and Display, The Enormous Egg A Full-Hour Color Special, Family and Trip Photographs, Oliver Butterworth and Treasury Department, Memorial Service for Oliver Butterworth, Galley Proof of Bud Oliver Butterworth's Letters from New Hampshire 1934-1937. Kent School Athletic Hall of Fame, Outstanding Service Award, Man In Space, Sunset Farm Weekly. Books Include: Bud Oliver Butterworth's Letters from New Hampshire 1934-1937, Essay on Nature, The Book.